<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Miserere cleri, a sermon, presenting the miseries of the clergy, and assigning their true causes in order to redress preached before the right honourable Sir John Vaughan Knight, Lord Chief Justice of His Majesties Court of common pleas, and Sir John Archer Knight, one of the justices of the same court : in the cathedral of Saint Peter, Exon, at the Assizes, on Sunday, July 26, 1688 / by Edw. Wetenhall ...</title>
            <author>Wettenhall, Edward, 1636-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65548</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1505</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3625</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11790746</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11790746</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49191</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65548)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49191)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 556:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Miserere cleri, a sermon, presenting the miseries of the clergy, and assigning their true causes in order to redress preached before the right honourable Sir John Vaughan Knight, Lord Chief Justice of His Majesties Court of common pleas, and Sir John Archer Knight, one of the justices of the same court : in the cathedral of Saint Peter, Exon, at the Assizes, on Sunday, July 26, 1688 / by Edw. Wetenhall ...</title>
                  <author>Wettenhall, Edward, 1636-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 25 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. N. for James Collins and are to be sold by Abisha Brocas ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>In the Savoy [London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bristol Public Library, Bristol, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Jeremiah XV, 10 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49191:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Miſerere Cleri.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON, PRESENTING THE MISERIES of the CLERGY, AND Aſsigning their true Cauſes in order to Redreſs: Preached before the Right Honourable Sir <hi>John Vaughan</hi> Knight, Lord Chief Juſtice of His Majeſties Court of Common Pleas, and Sir <hi>John Archer</hi> Knight, one of the Juſtices of the ſame Court.</p>
            <p>In the Cathedral of Saint <hi>Peter, Exon,</hi> at the Aſſizes, on <hi>Sunday, July</hi> 26. 1668.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> EDW. WETENHALL, one of the Prebendaries of that Church</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>In the <hi>SAVOY,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. N.</hi> for <hi>James Collins,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Abiſha<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Brocas</hi> Book-ſeller in <hi>Exon.</hi> 1668.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49191:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49191:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful JOHN TUCKFIELD Eſq. Sheriff of the County of <hi>Devon.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ere it not an unpardonable tranſgreſſion of Decorum to inſinuate any thing I preſent to you on common inducements, I ſhould (which moſt juſtly I might) have uſed the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſtyle of Dedications, and ſaid, The Vaſt Obligations, which you have laid upon me, require ſome publick teſtimony of gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titude, and I could never evidence it more proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than by making that yours, of which you were an Auditour in ſo publick a capacity.</p>
            <p>But I had rather the world ſhould know I am ignorant where to find a ſurer Patron for a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of this ſubject; and that your real Zeal and fidelity to the Eccleſiaſtical laws, order and preſent conſtitution, renders you, firſt a refuge of the conſtant and faithful ſons of the Church, and then of whatſoever ſpeaks ſuch faithfulneſs. Where therefore I am aſſured of ſo true affection to the
<pb facs="tcp:49191:3"/> Clergy, I cannot doubt but their Miſeries will find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſie Pity, and their Mournings Patronage: And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his is the true reaſon which gives you the Trouble of this Addreſs.</p>
            <p>If there ſhould be any expreſsion in what I haſtily meditated (as my neceſſary imploiments at preſent enforce) which ſhould diſguſt any, and create wonder that your name ſhould be uſed to authoriſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ught ſo harſh, you may be pleaſed to anſwer (what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s most true) That you knew neither of the Printing nor Dedication hereof till the ſight of it ſurprized you; That I am a man preſumptuous upon my friends, and had the boldneſs to reckon you one of the chief; That I did this (for what you know) on mine own head, and, poſſibly, carried away herein by an uncontroleable ambition of publiſhing my ſelf happy that I can pretend to be,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Of your ſervants (though) the meaneſt, Edw. Wetenhall.</signed>
               <dateline>Exon. <date>Aug. 1. 1668</date>.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49191:3"/>
            <head>Miſerere Cleri.</head>
            <head type="sub">A Sermon preached in the Cathedral of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter, Exon.</hi> on the Aſſize-<hi>Sunday, July</hi> 26. 1668.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>The Text JEREM. XV. 10.</bibl>
               <q>Wo is me my Mother, that thou hast born me a Man of ſtrife and contention to the whole earth: I have neither lent on <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, nor have men lent to me on <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, yet every one of them do curſe me.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Atience doth not exclude a ſenſe of Miſery, nor contentedneſs ever ſeal up the lips againſt all complaints. There may as well be on ſome ſeaſons a querulous meekneſs as a patient grief: and the ſuffering Saints we in Scripture read of, have little leſs obliged mankind by their ſeeming indulging ſome eruption of paſſions, which ſhews us what innocently we may do, than by their bounding and temperating ſuch indulgences, which teacheth us what we ought to do. Truly, as it is ſome comfort in our ſadneſs to ſee, that our elder brethren, in our Lords houſe, have been in like condition with us, ſo it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49191:4"/> but erect and ſweetly cheer our ſinking minds, that we find them when in like condition, to have been alſo of like paſſions with our ſelves.</p>
            <p>The Man <hi>Moſes,</hi> in his more conſtant temper, was the meekeſt man on earth: yet, when ſurprized by the hateful proſpect of his peoples idolatries and revolt, in a tranſport of indignation he broke the Tables, which not onely the moſt ſacred Law in them written, but the writing of the Almighties own finger had hallowed.</p>
            <p>We have heard too of the Patience of <hi>Job,</hi> who though he never in all his miſery charged God fooliſhly, yet after the anguiſh of ſeven days and ſeven nights, when his grief was very great, and none ſpake a word unto him, then opened his mouth, and curſed his day. In which, though ſome Modern heads (for Ancients never did) have been pleaſed to conceive him to have ſinned, yet who underſtand the holy Language know, that that <hi>curſing</hi> which the Original word there uſed ſignifies is only a light eſteeming, vilifying, or ſpeaking diſhonourably of: and who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Poetry will be apt to think the whole Chapter, which is ſuppoſed to contein that malediction, is onely a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick Threnody or lofty lamentation of his unhappy ſelf: which not improbably may teach us, that Big griefs may be allowed not onely to ſigh, but to ſigh deep as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and flow in Language which may ſeem as ſwoln, as the breſts from whence it came.</p>
            <p>Hereof another preſident we have in the preſent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, if not ſo innocently Chap. 20. 15. yet in the text ſurely without any other guilt, than that of frailty and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane infelicity. His eyes and experience had been ſad witneſſes of the publike corruption and looſneſs of the age: Divine inſpiration had acquainted him of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching deſolation of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and captivity of its in habitants: Himſelf had denounced to them this dreadfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doom, and, that he might have prevented it, with al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> paſſionateneſs and inſtance conjured them to repentance,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49191:4"/> but, alas! without ſucceſs: He had beſides with the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt profuſion of affections, and all ſenſible expreſſions thereof lamented their imminent calamity, wiſhing <hi>his Eyes might run down with tears night and day</hi> inceſſantly, uſing the ſweeteſt terms, and ſtyling them <hi>the Virgin daughter</hi> of his people, who were moſt lewdly idolatrous and meretricious, and yet could neither, notwithſtanding the authority with which he came, perſwade the people 'twas true he ſaid, nor with all his tears induce them to think he was concerned touching their certain miſery. Finally, he had, with the moſt efficacious arguments he could imagine, pleaded and ſtriven with God for mercy in their behalf, and found him as inflexible as them; his anſwer not being onely a denial, but a proteſtation of reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute obſtinacie: <hi>Though Moſes and Samuel ſtood before me, ſaith the Lord, yet ſhould not my mind be turned toward them, but I would caſt them out of my ſight.</hi> And after all this, his ſucceſsleſneſs, both with them and the Almighty, the ſole reception, which all his paſt pains and preſent Zeal found, was, from the people, Oppoſition, hatred, and revilings, and from God further imployment in his thankleſs and (as to him it ſeemed) not onely bootleſs but vexatious office. All which ſeeing, and not apprehending himſelf on one ſide or t'other likely to do good, being now ſadly taught by his own particular experience, what <hi>Solomon</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in general delivered, that <hi>The day of death is better than the day of birth,</hi> as unable in ſilence longer to contein ſuch agonies of anguiſh, he burſts out, <hi>Wo is me my mother, that thou hast born me a ſon of ſtrife and contention to the whole earth. I have neither,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I wiſh it were not obvious to parallel amongſt us <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie</hi>'s caſe, and that not in a particular perſon or two, but in a publick body. Who inherit his office, inherit his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery: and we of the Miniſtry of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who are faithful to her laws and intereſt, may, and ſurely many of us often have not unjuſtly taken up this lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49191:5"/> 
               <hi>Wo is me my mother,</hi> my mother the Engliſh Church, <hi>that thou haſt born me a ſon of ſtrife and contention to the whole earth.</hi> We have neither practiſed <hi>extortion</hi> nor <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion,</hi> I could wiſh it could as truly be ſaid, we had never ſuffered either, <hi>and yet the people curſe us.</hi> Give me leave, I beſeech you, to conſider the <hi>inducements</hi> of this <hi>lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and you ſhall not find it groundleſs. Give me leave to conſider the <hi>lamentation it ſelf,</hi> and it ſhall not appear exceſſive or exorbitant. Give me leave, laſtly, to conſider <hi>its intent or deſign,</hi> and I hope the whole will not be found uſeleſs.</p>
            <p>Who acts without a reaſon acts not like a man; who without due reaſon, not at all like a ſober man. That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore none may ſuſpect the juſtice or prudence of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets complaint, I beſeech you attend unto its inducements (ſhall I ſay?) or inforcements; which were two; His preſent miſery, and its grounds. His miſery in being <hi>a ſon of ſtrife and contention to the whole earth,</hi> and <hi>curſed by all the people.</hi> The grounds hereof, negatively expreſt, <hi>I have neither lent upon uſury, nor have men lent to me on uſury:</hi> and poſitively inſinuated, <hi>My mother hath born me a ſon of ſtrife and contention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As miſeries ſeldome come ſingle, ſo is it more than one, under which our Prophet groans. His words ſpeak him to have met with Contentious oppoſitions, ſcornful ſleights, and malicious ſlanders.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he complains himſelf to be <hi>a man</hi> of ſtrife and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> contention to the whole earth, that is, to the Jewiſh world, all that of earth, to which he was yet known, or had to do with: Not, that he was a man given to ſtrifes, but that in the innocent and conſcientious diſcharge of his ſacred function he met with them from the impieties of men. Neither were the Courts oppreſt with his ſuits, nor the ſtreets with his raileries, nor the fields with his quarrels or riots: but while from God he <hi>told Judah</hi> of their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and Iſrael of their ſins and ſad approaching re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49191:5"/> while he would have perſwaded the world to grow better, and ſave juſtice the labour, and themſelves the pains of puniſhment, he is reputed by ſuch, who had no ſtomach to virtue, a man as it were made up of ſtrife: And while he is zealouſly concerned about their happineſs, and will not be put off with a ſingle or ſome few iterated repulſes, he is thought troubleſome for this his charitable and unwearied importunity, and branded by men, who were reſolved never to be guilty of changing to the better, for a contentious perſon; and <hi>his</hi> zeal, and <hi>their</hi> incorri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gibleneſs gave him the trouble of one ſort of ſtriving, while he could not force himſelf to ſuffer them to periſh quietly.</p>
            <p>Something of ſuch contentiouſneſs is common to all who are ſent on like errands with the Prophet. Men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly prove not eaſie Proſelytes to holy Life: nor is it a ſmall contention of labour which thoſe muſt undergo whoſe buſineſs it is to mend the world. Cuſtome and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will are not the moſt flexile things; eſpecially, where va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of pleaſures and ſenſible glories perſwade the ſtiffeſt adhaeſion to them. Indeed therefore every private Chriſtian is in ſome meaſure <hi>a man of ſtrife:</hi> for he that hath enemies, which he muſt engage and cannot eaſily vanquiſh, muſt either yield or contend for victory. But the Miniſtry, beſides the conteſts which they have with their own corruptions and other inviſible foes, common to them with the Chriſtian multitude, have many another ſtrife proper to their function.</p>
            <p>1. They have a <hi>ſtrife</hi> with the Infidelity of men. Thoſe whom in other matters we finde ſufficiently credulous and eaſy, in Religion often we can perſwade but little. Alas! the practices of the age have rendred it, not only the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon mode, but intereſt, to queſtion or reject the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Faith, to the end the braver minds, as they are thought, may not be precided, ſcope and advantage to defend their beloved Latitude of life: And thoſe very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49191:6"/> who will receive Novel curioſities upon conjectures and probable ſurmiſes of the very firſt Fundamentals of all Religion require demonſtrations; and tolerable would our contention be, would they either acquieſce in them given, or not account every thing overthrown which they have been pleaſed to droll upon.</p>
            <p>Not leſs (2.) are our conteſts with misbelief than with unbelief. The Enemy who ſowed tares ſeems to have ſet out but little after the <hi>good ſeeds-man:</hi> and his evil ſeed both quickly ſprung up, and hath all along been fruitful. Verily, hath he not ſervants ſtill at work, whom while we ſtrive to counter-work and ſuppreſs, are we not repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted men of ſtrife: perſons who by making a clamour of <hi>damnable</hi> doctrines ſtirre up the Magiſtrate to perſecutions and ſeverities, and who obſtruct the happy liberty and flouriſhing of the Kingdome? That is, in truth, who at preſent (and 'tis but a little) ſtand in ſome mens way, that they cannot do the miſchief they would, or make the world as vitious, giddy and unhappy as themſelves. A ſad thing that ſuch liberty ſhould be denied men!</p>
            <p>But (3.) we are yet further <hi>men of ſtrife,</hi> for we have daily conteſts with the evil manners of the world, and are ſtudying and ſtriving with all our might and main, to bring Godlineſs and Honeſty, and Temperance and Charity into publick faſhion, and, if it might be, univerſal pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. In proſecution of which deſign, we many times meet with other contention, beſides that of labour. For when men cannot ſlight Gods worſhip, or cheat or revel, or maintain malice, but they muſt hear of it, it is no wonder if they, who quarrel with reformation of life, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat not well ſuch who would reform them.</p>
            <p>But that which makes this ſtrife ſo irkſome, and, as it were, impregnates it with woe, is, its frequent unſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and notwithſtanding perpetual incumbency. Men will not be perſwaded to <hi>Faith,</hi> to <hi>ſoundneſs,</hi> to Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, yet ſtill muſt we ſtrive on, and call and conjure and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49191:6"/> every way ſtruggle to reclaim their diſobedient and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying minds. And, ſpeed or not ſpeed, ceaſe we muſt not: Our being quiet were to betray thoſe who count us contentious for ſpeaking, and, our very ſilence would cry for vengeance on our ſelves, whatever it would bring on them who are ſo fond on it. Is not then this our work and function, as the caſe ſtands, a real miſery. If we hold our peace, albeit after rejection, we are ſound guilty. A <hi>neceſsity is laid upon me, and wo is me, if I preach not the Goſpel.</hi> If we preach, we generally ſtirre up the minds of ſuch againſt us, whoſe vices we have taxt; we embroil our ſelves in freſh heats, and, Wo is me, for thus, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>a man of ſtrife and contention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I will be bold to avouch this ſtrife innocent, though troubleſome, and of moſt worthy and profitable deſign. 'Tis onely great vice which makes our work ſtrife and then is pleas'd to brand us for contentious; who in truth, in all theſe conteſts are but dutiful towards God, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men charitable and compaſſionate. And, being the ſtrife, which exerciſeth us, is of this nature, give me leave to ſay, 'Tis ſuch which will not misbecome perſons of the greateſt honour and intereſt to aſſiſt us in. The ſword of peace, and they who bear it, may do much for the aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the heat of theſe conflicts, which chiefly, I ſay, riſeth from the boldneſs, and that boldneſs from the impunity of vice. Let me therefore humbly crave that no opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty may be omitted which offers it ſelf for the puniſhment of Irreligious, unſound and lewd perſons. With theſe, alas! the poor Prophets have ſtriven, and ſtriven long many of us, and unſucceſsfully, and are for our labours, onely reputed <hi>men of contention.</hi> But when perſons of power interpoſe, the engagement will not be to them mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſtrife, but victory. He that threatens and cannot ſtrike, becomes ridiculous by his impotence: and they who have enjoyed long impunity eaſily contemn future vengeance, which their experience tempts them to think
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49191:7"/> will be ever future. But he who checkes ill manners and together can and will puniſh them, is alone by audacious offenders reputed to <hi>ſpeak with Authority:</hi> and pardon me, I beſeech you, whoever may think your ſelves concern'd, if I again requeſt you ſo to ſpeak, where your own prudence and fidelity, not my impertinence ſhall direct.</p>
            <p>I ſhall account my ſelf to have ſaid enough to the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, being men <hi>of ſtrife and contention,</hi> when I have deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my brethren to be men of no other <hi>ſtrifes,</hi> than thoſe I have alledged to engage all of us in common. It is an hateful thing to ſee any man frequent at Courts, ſave thoſe who come thither to ſerve their Country (and their feet I could even kiſs that they bring them thither) but of all men to ſee a Miniſter wear out his ſhooes, or tire his horſe by going to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> or every aſſize is moſt abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Neceſſity indeed may acquit, grand convenience ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuſe; Jealouſies, projects, or ſelf-pleaſing humours are no Pleas of innocence but guilt.</p>
            <p>Our Prophets ſecond miſery, which preſſed from him <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> this <hi>Wo is me,</hi> was ſcornful ſlights and Undervaluings. For we muſt know, if we take curſing ſtrictly for malicious im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precations, the rendring, <hi>Every one curſeth me,</hi> is not the moſt exact: the word original not being oppoſed to <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> but <hi>honouring.</hi> But in its Hebrew notion, as curſing many times ſignifies ſlighting, extenuating or contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptive language, (ſuch curſing as undutiful children are guilty of towards their parents, when they render to them diſreſpective terms where honourable ones are due) it is well admiſſible. And this it ſeems the Prophet was ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to have met with in ſuch meaſure, that the Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint (though poſsibly miſtaking <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and then ſupplying the ſuppoſed <hi>Ellipſis</hi>) and others from them, have not doubted to render his words, <hi>My ſtrength hath failed me amongſt thoſe that curſe me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our ſtrength indeed fails us not yet, becauſe there is ſuch a thing as hope, not only that the contemptuous
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49191:7"/> world may in time bethink themſelves of better manners, but that there is a bleſsing which awaits thoſe, who have been reviled for Righteouſneſs ſake: and we are apt to think, that to be ſlighted for being Miniſters, that is, Embaſſadours of Chriſt to perſwade men to their own happineſs and trueſt intereſt; may be adjudged a caſe of righteouſneſs in one world or t'other. But yet can we not at preſent (and alas moſt pertinently) take up that the old Churches bemoaning addreſſe, <hi>Have mercy upon us, O Lord, have mercy upon us, for we are exceedingly filled with contempt. Our ſoul is exceedingly filled with the Scorning of thoſe that are at eaſe, and with the contempt of the proud;</hi> to whom notwithſtanding we beſeech thee, Lord, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der nothing but <hi>Mercy, Pardon,</hi> and <hi>Repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is yet more of miſery which brought <hi>Jeremy,</hi> thus <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> as it were before his time to his <hi>Lamentations.</hi> To oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and affronts were added ſlanders of no leſs malice than forgery and impudence. <hi>Come,</hi> ſaid they, and <hi>let us deviſe deviſes againſt Jeremiah.——Come, let us ſmite him with the tongue, and let us not give heed unto any of his words.</hi> His words were the precepts of heaven and rules for holy living: now theſe becauſe they had no minde to entertain or ſuffer, they reſolve on the deviſing ſome ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal to caſt on his perſon, and ſo to blaſt his Miniſtery whom they could not ſilence.</p>
            <p>Oh! that there were but ſo much Innocence in the age, that I wanted a parallel to this impious Stratagem! But is it not as clear as the Sun, that now when Religion it ſelf hath been long decryed as a fondneſs, and the idol of weaker reaſons, by men who pretend to have engroſſed all maſculine wiſdom; when Chriſtianity (to ſay nothing of Chriſt its founder) hath been publickly affronted by ſuch who ſeem to reckon drollery, ſcorns and lewdneſs, the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excellencies of the rational life, and yet both Religion in the general and Chriſtianity particularly, ſeemed ſtill in the poſſeſſion of their ancient authority and eſteem, not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49191:8"/> only the people being generally tenacious of them, but there being a certain order of men, of learning, gravity and ſome influence upon the multitude, whoſe buſineſs it is both to defend and propagate this holy doctrine; perſons of the Character now given, have made it their work to draw an <hi>Odium</hi> and contempt on that Order, moſt vily aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſing ſome (and making but a jeſt of it, when they had done) and involving the whole body in more general im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, which would be ſure to blaſt their repute and intereſt, wherever thoſe imputations could be received, and ſo make their teſtimonies of little effect to promote virtue, which it is before hand inſinuated, they have no regard for themſelves.</p>
            <p>This, this then being our condition, that our work is perpetual contention with the infidelity, factiouſneſs, ſchiſms, and other ill manners of men, and, which renders this the more troubleſome, that though we have long without ſucceſs contended, we muſt ſtill with utmoſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour proceed, that notwithſtanding all our old and preſent buſying our heads, and concerning our very ſouls for men, beſides oppoſition we receive, all abroad, moſt bitter ſlights, are reputed as the filth of the world and the moſt impertinent of all things, a ſort of men who were found in the world and muſt live, but are permitted to live onely clouded with a multitude of black aſperſions; This, I ſay, being the condition of the very chief of us and all in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, what can be expected more naturally from us, if we may be ſuppoſed to attend unto our miſery, than <hi>Woe is me my Mother that thou haſt borne me a man of ſtrife and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the whole earth!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But bleſſed be God, it is to Earth only that we are repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuch: (Our <hi>contention</hi> being in the cauſe of <hi>Heaven,</hi> we have it our Friend.) And not to <hi>every</hi> one <hi>on earth</hi> neither, but to ſuch onely who bear the Character of Earth (are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) ſons of Violence or obſcurity, the meaner or worſer ſort, as earth the dregs of nature, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49191:8"/> ſuch whoſe ſouls ſeem made of mud too, as minding onely earthly or more vile things. There are ſome more generous and heaven-born minds (and I am confident I ſpeak before ſeveral ſuch at preſent) who having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the hidden things of diſhoneſty and diſhonoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs, all <hi>infidely,</hi> and bad principles and vileneſs, both ſtand up for the worſhip of God, and think a ſlovenly and diſorderly worſhip not worthy his glory; who are not fond to ſee their prieſts in rags, nor the faces or of them or theirs pale with leanneſs. The Lord give mercy unto ſuch in that day. And to all ſuch, who are conſcious to themſelves of ſo worthy minds (and it is not our fault if any be not) we in all humility addreſſing our ſelves, beſeech, what we complain of as the reception we find from the generality, none of them think in the leaſt to reflect upon himſelf. Even in the text, thoſe general words [<hi>A man of contention to the whole earth,</hi> and, <hi>Every one of them,</hi> or rather <hi>All them,</hi> that is the generality, and ſome of all ſorts, <hi>curſe me</hi>] were not intended by <hi>Jeremiah</hi> to deſign the whole humane nature, no, nor all of the Jewiſh nation. There were of them that hid <hi>Jeremiah</hi> and <hi>Baruch,</hi> and ſtood as a skreen between him and the wrath of the King. There were that viſited him in the dungeon, and lift him thence, and brought him again unto the King, and procured favour and kinder uſage for him. And verily, <hi>Except the</hi> Lord had left unto us ſuch a remnant, we ſhould have been as Sodom, and we ſhould have been like unto Gomorrah. But bleſſed be him that remembred us in our low eſtate, and hath made Kings our nurſing Fathers, and Queens our nurſing Mothers; Inſomuch that ſtill our remnant, God be thanked, is larger much than was that of the Prophets friends: And we hope he will yet remember us. For truly, ſuch ſtill is our low eſtate (if to be matter of the common trample be to be low) that we need the conſtancy and endeavours of all our friends, were they more numerous much than they are. And in confidence of the kind reception of what we ſpeak
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49191:9"/> to ſuch, we will adventure to lay our miſery yet farther open, by proceeding unto its grounds, firſt, Negatively expreſſed in the text, <hi>I have neither lent on uſury, nor have men lent to me on uſury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I intend not here at all to enter upon the common place of Uſury: It ſhall ſuffice onely to ſay, that the Old Uſury in practice amongſt the Jews was widely different from that which our Law permits. The precept which allowed it to them was ſo far from ſetting bounds to their avarice, that it ſeems to have enlarged its mouth, at leaſt as <hi>ſin took occaſion by the law.</hi> For the Law determining Uſury lawful to be exacted onely upon Gentiles, not brethren Jews (and moſt probably on the ſeven Nations, whom God had command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to afflict and caſt out, though afterwards, for their puniſhment, he ſuffered the remains of them to co-inhabit the Holy Land with his people) the Jews thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not onely allowed but in a ſort obliged (by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of afflicting them) by all means to extort from them all they could. Hence it came to paſs that where-ever they lent on uſury (which by degrees they did to other than thoſe ſeven Nations, indeed to any whoſe needs made them borrowers) they made all the advantages they could on the neceſſity of the borrower, and oppreſſion, extortion or grinding the face of the poor, became the ſame thing with Uſury, as not onely the Hebrew, but many of the Oriental names for Uſury ſtill import. Whereas I ſuppoſe our laws which ſtate Uſury puniſh Extortion. Whence it is concluſible, that they who urge texts of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with ſo much heat againſt the preſent <hi>Uſe</hi> amongſt us, do not ſpeak <hi>Ad idem,</hi> if <hi>ad idem nominis,</hi> not <hi>rei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as to the Clergy in this caſe, I wiſh fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt number of them were as able to purge themſelves of the latter clauſe, that they have not <hi>taken on uſury,</hi> as they are of the former, that they have not <hi>lent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to quit the whole matter in ſo ſtrict an acception. It is the obſervation of a learned Textuary, that under the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49191:9"/> one kind of Borrowing and Lending, he compriſes all other matters which men uſe to tranſact among themſelves in point of dealing or Traffick. And ſo undoubtedly the ſumme of what the Prophet meant is more general; yet reducible to theſe two points: He had neither been guilty in any caſe of rigorous <hi>exaction</hi> of what was his own, nor of <hi>Detention,</hi> or undue holding, what was anothers: No one had matter of <hi>contention</hi> with him in things of this nature, nor could for theſe any man <hi>curſe him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſure for the Clergy generally I have the ſame plea to enter.</p>
            <p>1. It is not for any Extortion or ſevere Exaction that we meet with ſuch oppoſition and obloquy as what at preſent we labour under. I know indeed there are who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count receiving of Tithes, and ſuch revenues, which antient nurſing Fathers and Mothers bequeathed to the Church, to be Exaction. But ſuch muſt pardon us if we think what bounty gives, indigent induſtry may harmleſly receive, and further crave, it may be thought hard, that ſuch, who will not give us any thing themſelves, ſhould ſeek to take away from us the antient Donations of others. I have heard that they who have been unqueſtionably learned in the Law, have ſaid, that he underſtands not how he holds his Lands, who thinks his Tithes his own: and that there is not the Family now in being, which can plead in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interrupted line to have enjoyed any Poſſeſſions neer ſo long as the Church hath done this of Tithes: much leſs which hath had <hi>revenues</hi> ſettled by half ſo many Statutes and legal Securities as theſe. But as to this of <hi>Tithes</hi> and other Church-revenues, I ſhall onely be bold to ſpeak in my own Profeſsion, uſing too the words of one vaſtly abler than my ſelf therein. That God accepts of things<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Hammond.</hi>
               </note> given him and ſo holds a Propriety, as well in the New as Old Teſtament, and, That God gets this Propriety in thoſe things he holds, as well by an acceptation of what is voluntarily given, as by a command that ſuch things
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49191:10"/> ſhould be preſented to him is moſt clear from Scripture. The known caſe of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira</hi> will prove it. And that he accounts himſelf to receive by the hands of his ſervants who want it, is no leſs evident from that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, <hi>I was hungry and ye fed me, naked and ye clothed me, ſick and ye viſited me, &amp;c.</hi> In a word, it is as much as if he ſaid, Food, Raiment, and Neceſſaries, as well in ſickneſs as in health, ye the true Righteous Ones have provided for me: ye have, as farre as was poſſible to you, provided for me the Head (who abſolutely in my ſelf am above the ſphere of your bounty) while your <hi>goodneſs,</hi> which could <hi>not extend to me,</hi> hath imparted <hi>to the Saints</hi> my members <hi>which are on earth.</hi> And we cannot ſuppoſe (as my incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Authour proceeds) that he would take meat, and refuſe revenues, or like being fed and clothed to day, and being in danger to be ſtarved to morrow. No more can we think, that the wanting perſons in whom he accounted himſelf to be fed, clothed and ſupported were only Laicks, as we ſpeak, perſons to be inſtructed, not at all their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructers: For it were a ſtrange thing to affirm, Chriſt liked it extreme well to be fed and clothed in all His but onely his Apoſtles or Seventy Diſciples. Beſides touching them expreſly he ſpeaks, <hi>He that receiveth you receiveth me,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Matth. 10. 40, &amp;c.</hi> In ſumme then, it was lawful for thoſe antient Saints, our Founders and Benefactours to give: it was not onely a lawful but good work, for they have rewards promiſed and approportioned to them for their giving: and further, their giving makes the things given Gods, that is, the Churches his Proxy. Our laws ſettle the Donation: where then is the Exaction in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving? The rigour with which any exact their dues, together with the (ſeemingly) unhandſome management of ſuch matters, if the particular neceſſitous conditions of ſuch perſons and the provocations of the deteinours do not excuſe or alleviate, yet may not be extended beyond the particular perſons guilty, and ſo is no crime of the body.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49191:10"/> It is evident then, that 'tis not for <hi>Exactions</hi> that we fare or hear thus hardly:</p>
            <p>And the reflexion on what we have ſaid will evince, that it is not (2.) for unjuſt Detention neither. For if what we hold be, both by the law of God and our good Kings, our own, we cannot be ſaid, for holding it, deteinours of anothers. Poſſibly ſome may ſay, all was not given us to raiſe to our ſelves vaſt eſtates, to live in the greateſt pomp, ſplendour, and eaſe; but after neceſſary ſuſtenance of our ſelves, to feed the hungry, to cloth the naked, and entertain indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſtrangers, and not ſolely our rich friends. I moſt gladly grant all this: and certainly there are not a few of the able Clergy who do this, only they deſire to be excuſed if they do not ſound trumpets to it; and as to thoſe, who being able do it not, I know no man of ſo baſe a ſpirit as to undertake their defence.</p>
            <p>There may be haply ſome who may account gratitude next to charity, and ſay, not unreaſonably, we ſhould out of our abundance conſider more liberally ſuch who have ſuffered for us. Alas! ſhould every ſuffering Friend of the Church be according to merit gratified out of its revenues, the whole would not ſuffice to pay that one debt. And if any alledge we have found wherewith to gratifie enemies, let that onely lie at the door of the guilty, and then I am ſure it will lie nor at all nor at moſt of the Clergies; amongſt whom, if where there is an impotence of paying other thanks, prayers and love, and honour, and offices of kindneſs and Chriſtianity, might be reckoned as acts of gratitude, I hope there are very few will be found ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. Notwithſtanding even theſe charges therefore, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of us can moſt truly ſay, that if we lie under con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and infamy, and are ſtruck at by any at preſent, it is not either for <hi>Exaction</hi> or <hi>Detention.</hi> What the Clergy receives or holds at preſent is juſtly theirs; nor is it evident, the premiſes being conſidered, how any other can receive or hold the ſame without <hi>Sacriledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:49191:11"/>
            <p>I have done with what is not the cauſe of our Miſery: but I ſaid ſomething of what is its cauſe was poſitively in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuated in the text, and ſo it is in thoſe words, <hi>My Mother thou haſt born me a Man of ſtrife and contention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Infants indeed when born, they ſay, cry: but their little wrangles have more of Miſery than Contention: How then had his Mother born him ſuch? Or why cries he out of an innocent Parent? Was ſhe acceſſary to his Miſery, becauſe inſtrumental to his being? No: this was not it. <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> we muſt know, was the ſon of <hi>Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> of the Prieſts that were in <hi>Anathoth</hi> in the land of <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin:</hi> and being the ſon of a Prieſt he was ſo farr forth born a Prieſt; for as ſuch he was actually to be admitted as ſoon as by age ſerviceable for his office. The ſumme then of what he complains of, as from his Mother was, Becauſe thou haſt born me <hi>a Prieſt, thou haſt born me a Man of ſtrife and contention.</hi> And all us who were from our Births by providence deſtin'd to the ſame Office, ſeem alſo ſet forth as men appointed to the like Miſery; Perſons who have an Office devolv'd upon us to tell men of their faults, to awaken a thing call'd <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which the luxury and affected liberty of the age hath no mind to hear; and beſides this are to live upon Tithes, or that more envied matter Church-revenues. Ah! hence, hence are we <hi>Men of contention</hi> and <hi>curſed</hi> by the multitude. But part of this Miſery hath been already toucht, and the reſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps it is better ſilently to devour, than to let the world hear of it, leaſt any ſhould be angry alſo that we feel it.</p>
            <p>Are there then no cauſes of this your Miſery amongſt your ſelves? will ſome ſay: none too, which argue gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lt on your ſide?</p>
            <p>Alas! if <hi>I knew none</hi> yet would I not juſtifie us; for he that judgeth is the Lord. But there are faults, and thoſe too viſible, though haply not the ſame with them which are commonly charged upon us. To wit,</p>
            <p>1. Fawning and baſe Compliances for advantage or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49191:11"/> quiets ſake is a fault many of us cannot acquit our ſelves of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This, as ſoon as perceived, blaſts our authority with the perceiver, and expoſeth us to contempt: and 'tis ſure, Contemne me this moment, and hate me the next, and then immediately enter all the conſequents of conceived hate, Oppoſitions, calumnies, affronts, &amp;c. Again,</p>
            <p>2. Affectation of too ſplendid and courtly living is no friend nor virtue of many of the Clergy. Courtly living I call that, when we cannot furniſh our houſes nor tables, but both appear emulous of thoſe of Noblemen; and the clothes our families wear, or faſhions they go in, are ſuch that our neighbours of beſt condition are fain to ſtretch their eſtates, and perhaps be as laviſh of their time, to dreſs and go ſo fine as ours do. This expoſeth us to envy, as the other to contempt, and an envied perſon can never live without oppoſers and detractours.</p>
            <p>3. Another fault amongſt us which begets us no love is Vain-glory, and derogating from others of our brethren to adde unto our ſelves. We make one another <hi>curſed,</hi> that is meanly or evil ſpoken of, becauſe ſome of us have a mind to fly loftier in the mouths of men than we do deſerve. Some of us would have our parts admired, and others our pains, and others ſomewhat elſe: and accordingly when we meet with opportunities to our minds we ſlily inſinuate, ſuch a mans preaching is at beſt dull and liveleſs, ſuch and ſuch are lazy and more ſtudious of the fleece than flock, &amp;c. And few hearers now-adays but can underſtand the perſons deſigned, by general characters, without particular names or indigitations. Thus in Cathedrals we hear our ſelves called lazy, by many who cannot be ignorant we miniſter weekly elſewhere, but are willing, to the end their dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence may be admired, that the people ſhould think we never preach but when in our courſes (which thoſe onely who ſeldomeſt come here, think moſt ſlowly to return) we ſerve this audience. I have no mind to exagitate, or drive this general through all the ſeverals I might: but in ſumme,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49191:12"/> it is no wonder if when we bring <hi>railing accuſations</hi> (though cunningly) againſt one another, the people at leaſt learn thus much, that they ſay after us.</p>
            <p>4. Further, No ſmall occaſion of Evil and Evil-ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to us is the <hi>ſeeking great things for our ſelves</hi> and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. We profeſs to teach ſelf-denial and contempt of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular glories: we therefore evidently contradict our ſelves when moderate proviſions ſuffice us not. And the truth is; Graſping at too large eſtates is neither ſafe to us nor our poſterity as to the general. Not to us, inaſmuch as none can grow great without envy: (Whether St. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſpoke it out of Diſcontent or in ſobriety, it is ſtrangely ſunk into moſt mens minds, as their practice ſpeaks. <hi>Clericum ex inope divitem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quaſi quandam peſtem fuge.</hi>) Nor to our poſterity, for wiſe men have obſerved that the children of Clergy-men, who have been with mean for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes put into ways of living or thriving by their own induſtry, have more perpetuated their fathers names and honours, than thoſe who having been amply bred have been left as amply provided for. Their parents have made them Gentlemen, and their own negligence Beggars. It is then more than double imprudence to venture mine own ruine, that I may expoſe my ſons to the ſame fate. Laſtly</p>
            <p>5. I cannot deny, but there are amongſt us who are guilty of encroachment upon the lower Clergy. The abuſe of Diſpenſations and Pluralities in ſuch caſes where nothing but ſome mens inſatiableneſs requires them, breeds many a negligent incumbent, many an unſufficient Curate, and a great deal of hate, obloquy and contempt to our whole order. But I am an unfit perſon to ſpeak hereof, and ſay not what I would in this caſe, leaſt, in any thing I ſay, diſcontent ſhould ſeem to prompt me.</p>
            <p>I might poſſibly enlarge this Catalogue on our ſide, but am more ways than one ſtraitned. Onely I cannot but crave leave to adde, that there are ſeveral faults too on the ſide
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49191:12"/> of the people, which we are not at all acceſſary to, which notwithſtanding bring vexation and reproaches in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on the moſt innocent of our body. I ment on them not by way of upbraiding but as ſupplicating for their refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
            <p>1. Firſt, it is certain that a luxurious age will never ſhine upon the Clergy: I onely wiſh this may not prove one.</p>
            <p>2. Another evil no leſs miſchievous to us, is, that the Multitude are and have been a long time venim'd with factious and ſchiſmatical principles, which late diſorders have infuſed; and from this perverſe abundance proceed anſwerable practices.</p>
            <p>3. With the humour of theſe male-contents ſtrike in thoſe, who as good as profeſs to be of no religion, yet have told the world they can be of any; in hopes that if the on-both-ſides-maligned Church ſhould fall, they may ſhare either in the booty, or liberty, which will accrue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon. And upon the whole from the <hi>Genius</hi> and infections of both ariſeth an impoſſibility for us (eſpecially if we ſtick to our engagements of conformity) generally to pleaſe. If we ſtudy to ſpeak ſenſe, and deliver what we have me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditated without affectation, we are dull Preachers. If we play the <hi>Zanies</hi> and <hi>Jack Puddings</hi> in the Pulpit, weak people admire and ſober loath both us and <hi>the offerings of the Lord.</hi> If we preach ſeldom, though well, we are idle: if frequently, we preach too often poſſibly to preach well<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Thus,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Obſtat, chare Pudens; noſtris tua turba libellis,</l>
               <l>Lectoremque frequens laſſat &amp; implet opus.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Again, if we preach neceſſaries, that is, preſs Virtues and Holy life, we are onely Legal-Preachers: if we inveigh againſt popular vices we rail: but if againſt our Governours we pleaſe indeed a great (and I fear the greater) part, but then we become factious with them. And ſeriouſly, this very impoſſibility of pleaſing (notwithſtanding all our ſtudies and prayers) I could almoſt proteſt makes me
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49191:13"/> alone well-nigh weary of my function: but I do confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently avow that this, occaſioned as beforeſaid is the firſt and chiefeſt cauſe of all our miſery; of all the Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, affronts, and ill reports we meet with.</p>
            <p>4. The laſt rock, which I will point at, threatning us with wrack is the projections and contrivances of ſome who are taken (rather by themſelves than other competent judges) for deep and prudent men. They could, in ſhort, better mold the laws (Civil and Eccleſiaſtical) relieve the Subject, promote publick intereſts, were thoſe laid aſide, who ſtand ſo importunately to this, that one Religion or Profeſſion of it ſhould in this Church lord it over all other.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt caſe; that men ſhould ſtill be attempting the amendment of our Frame of Government, I confeſs I am truly amaz'd. Good God! Are we not yet weary of <hi>Rota's?</hi> Have we not been tumbled yet often enough <hi>from one veſſel to another?</hi> Surely it is now at length time to ſettle, if all of us in ſtead of brains wear not quickſilver. The Ancients accounted our Country one of the <hi>Fortunate Iſlands:</hi> Truly it would ſoon be ſuch, if its inhabitants would once ceaſe their <hi>Eutopian</hi> Projects.</p>
            <p>As to the other of relieving the Subject by the ruine of the Church, I had almoſt ſaid, it is the groſſeſt abuſe of God, Religion and the Truth, and beſides of the King and People, that can be imagined. <hi>In omni Religione nihil tale ſine Vindicta</hi> was of old the aged and learned <hi>Lactantius</hi> his obſervation. And can we think, if there be any Truth in Religion or the being of a God, that he, who hath ever avenged the cauſe of mock-gods, when ſacriledge hath been committed on what was devoted to them, will be leſs Zealous in his own honour and cauſe? Give me leave a little, I beſeech you: What is become of greater revenues alienated from the Church than thoſe at preſent remaining to Cathedrals? Is the Crown richer for them? Or the people eaſier? Or would what is left ſatisfie? And how long?</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49191:13"/>
            <p>You ſee I repreſs my ſelf: and to the end you may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our Miſery is great, I ſhall onely adde, that beſides what we have lamented to you, there is yet much remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which we keep to our ſelves, intending our complaint ſhall be like <hi>Jeremie</hi>'s, moderate not exorbitant, which I ſhall briefly touch on, as being the ſecond thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed.</p>
            <p>Our Prophet ſeeing ſo much contention, ſo much ſcorn, ſo much obloquy attend him, and that meerly becauſe of his Office and care in its diſcharge, which as to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had ſo much pains and thankleſneſs in it, yet ſo happy a deſign as to others, thus bemoans himſelf, <hi>Wo is me my Mother, that thou haſt born me a Man of ſtrife, &amp;c.</hi> In other words, Miſerable, woful man that I am! He doth not ſay, Wo is me that I was born, but <hi>that I was born a man of ſtrife and contention,</hi> that is, a Prieſt, and ſanctified from the womb to be a Prophet. He complains his office had much of <hi>Wo</hi> in it: and the premiſes conſidered, Had not his? Hath not ours? Yet,</p>
            <p>1. As <hi>Jeremy</hi> did not, ſo neither do we relinquiſh our Office for its burden. Such regards of <hi>Fame</hi> we leave as proper to many of our <hi>Factious Detractours;</hi> being reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved our ſelves <hi>to bear</hi> the Clouds as well as <hi>Heat and burden of the day.</hi> Being therefore we are (through Divine grace) thus reſolutely diligent in our Lords vineyard, we hope nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he nor any juſt judge will reckon it to us as a crime, that having ſuch a load on us, it preſſeth from our labouring hearts now and then a groan: Eſpecially when we</p>
            <p>2. Do not (as, nor here doth <hi>Jeremy</hi>) accuſe our God that he hath laid our burden ſo heavy. Poſſibly 'tis our unskilfulneſs or miſcarriage that hath, as to our ſenſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanc't its weight: Our ſins haply have added unto its preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and the load would ſit much eaſier were our ſhoulders better qualified, or had we laid aſide every other weight: At the worſt, the day haſtens apace when we (perſevering) ſhall <hi>reſt from our labours;</hi> and then, no more weight, but
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49191:14"/> that of glory, which the preſent preſſures (that then will ſeem, not onely light, but ſweet in their memory and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards) ſhall exceedingly and eternally adde unto. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as we faint not, ſo neither do we murmur or</p>
            <p>3. Nor yet do we inveigh againſt men who thus load us with ſtrifes, ſlights, and calumnies; except the meer letting them know their ſins, ours as well as their own mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, be ſo interpreted. And as long as thus only, with <hi>Jeremy,</hi> we complain, with all ſubmiſſion to God, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to men, and reſolved diligence in our troubleſome work, we truſt we ſhall never be adjudged in any meaſure exceſſively querulous.</p>
            <p>But if theſe be not expreſſions of diſcontent, what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign have they? They have the ſame deſign as had <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy</hi>'s complaint in the Text, the View of which was the laſt thing propounded, and intended as the Application of all.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, as <hi>Jeremy,</hi> ſo we thus publiſh our miſeries to bring men to Relentings of heart and to Repentance for theſe ſtubbornneſſes and irreligiouſneſſes which will other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe deprive them of Eternal life, as at preſent they hinder thoſe, who deſign their happineſs and <hi>watch over their ſouls,</hi> of a quiet life. This is the reaſon of our vehemency, and clamours, as ſome may eſteem them. Alas! we have no diſpleaſure, no enmity or quarrel with the perſons of any men: we are adverſaries onely to their adverſaries, that is, their vices. Let men renounce but theſe, and we forthwith quit not onely all we ſeem'd to have againſt them, but our very opinion, ſenſe, and complaints of our own above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamented miſery. We change our <hi>Wo is me,</hi> into <hi>Bleſſed me,</hi> and Bleſſed my mother that haſt born me a man of ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſtrife and contention; for I have <hi>converted a ſinner from the errour of his wayes.</hi> Let me then moſt paſſionately im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune and beg of our oppoſers and detractours, if not for their own ſakes, and out of a regard to the immortal ſouls they wear, yet that out of ingenuity, out of generous and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49191:14"/> good natures to which they generally pretend, they will a little abate of their affronts and contempts of religion, (for upon that fall all the ſleights and reproaches which are caſt on us for our Profeſſions ſake;) that they will think men, who are ready to lay down their life for the truth of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve really what they teach of the truth of Religion; that they will exerciſe ſo much of ſobriety and good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as not always to anſwer, onely with laughter, ſerious reaſons and demonſtrations, in the verity of which ages and multitudes of moſt learned men have acquieſced; and not proceed to vex the ſouls of them, who moſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately deſire their welfare, with ſuch inſolent tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plings.</p>
            <p>Another deſign, which we may have in indulging theſe complaints, which it is not improbable too <hi>Jeremy</hi> might have in his eye, is, the putting our ſelves on a ſtrict enquiry, whether we owe not our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries to our crimes. The Prophet ſeems (I ſay) to have ſearched, when he pronounces, <hi>I have neither lent on uſury, nor have men lent to me on uſury.</hi> And I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech, in all reverence, all my brethren, that I may ſpeed in this deſign on them: if any of us particularly apprehend our ſelves <hi>men of ſtrife,</hi> &amp;c. in the ſenſe inſiſted on, let ſuch be pleaſed impartially to enquire, if themſelves be guiltleſs as to their own miſery. If they are not as to their own, it is certain they cannot be as to their brethrens. I know, none of thoſe, whom at preſent I addreſs my ſpeech to, want abilities to ſuggeſt more heads of ſacerdotal miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages then I have touched. Thoſe abilities and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine grace, which will be wanting to none in ſuch deſigns, improve to an honeſt ſcrutiny and Reformation, and it will undoubtedly much remedy both your own and others Woe.</p>
            <p>A third deſign, which in theſe complaints we truly have, and <hi>Jeremy</hi> might have, is, to move Perſons of Power and Place to our pity and Relief. Nor can I but perſwade my
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49191:15"/> ſelf, I have already ſped in my requeſt, where I am ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident juſtice dwells. The ſumme I crave is, all poſſible en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to ſerious Religion, and eſpecially to the profeſſion of it at preſent ſettled. With many, all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is decryed as an abuſe of credulous mankind: with others, either the preſent Religion amongſt us impugned or the ſtrictneſs (as is pretended) of its preſent ſettlement. Now nothing can contribute ſo much to the intereſt of Religion in common as the countenance of great and grave perſons. Nothing can do this particular profeſſion of it more ſervice than their vigorous adhaeſion to its laws. And remember, I beſeech you our late confuſions: Can any ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber man be fond on Hemms and Expletives and Non-ſenſe for Prayers, of confuſed Noiſes for Praiſes, of Ruines for Churches, or blue Aprons, and ſuch like cattle for Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Behold the goodly majeſty, yet gravity and modeſty of our preſent Order: The place auguſt; the prayers and Hymns certain, devout, complete; the Harmony full; they who miniſter, in a reverend decency, and each inſtructed and exerciſed in his faculty: The whole ſtriking a ſacred Awe and Veneration upon the Enterer, and ſo fitting him with an holy fear and tranſport of mind to fall down and worſhip the unſeen <hi>Beauty of Holineſs,</hi> the eſſential glory of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite God. Behold, I ſay, and conſider all; and let your ſouls ſeriouſly deprecate and abhorre the day, that ever the <hi>Axes</hi> and the <hi>Hammers</hi> ſhould be at work again in the Temple, except it be to repair its deficiencies, or that, for want of bread unto its Miniſters, the glory of Mount <hi>Sion</hi> ſhould become deſolate, and as a <hi>lodge in a garden of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In caſe theſe deſigns ſhould fail (which God forbid) we have yet one more; and that is by this view of our miſeries and theſe complaints and lamentations of it, to move our own, and all pious breſts to a moſt affectionate ardour and intenſneſs of Devotion, and thereby Him to pity, whoſe pity is together help, and alone powerful to turn our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49191:15"/> into Hallelujahs of joy, our fears into ſafety, and to make our <hi>mountain ſtand faſt.</hi> And to him are our eyes: <hi>We have looked for peace, but behold tottering; for the time of healing, but behold trouble: See, O Lord, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, we are become vile. We acknowledge, O Lord, our iniquities and the iniquity of our forefathers, for we have all ſinned againſt thee, Yet do not thou abhorre us ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much; For thy names ſake, do not diſgrace the throne of thy glory.</hi> Or, if ſo it is decreed, for our ſins, that we ſhall be ſcattered, Scatter us, O Lord, but let our diſperſions intirely praiſe thee, and find us out ſome Wilderneſs where we may in <hi>Order</hi> if not <hi>Decency,</hi> ſing, <hi>Glory be to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son and Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Glory be to God on high, and on earth Peace, Goodwill towards mankind. Amen, Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:49191:16"/>
            <head>Books printed and ſould by <hi>James Collins</hi> at the Kings Head in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FOurty Sermons of that famous Preacher M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Anthony Farindon. Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Triumphs of <hi>Rome</hi> over deſpiſed Proteſtancy, written by Biſhop <hi>Hall.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Flora Ceres &amp; Pomona:</hi> or, A Compleat Floriledge, by <hi>F. Rea</hi> Gent. <hi>Fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſiderations touching Witches and Witchcraft, with the fam'd Diſturbance of the <hi>Demon</hi> at <hi>Tedworth:</hi> and ſome other reflections on <hi>Drollery</hi> and <hi>Atheiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plus ultra,</hi> or the Advancement and Progreſs of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſince the days of <hi>Ariſtotle:</hi> both written by <hi>Joſ. Glanvil</hi> Fellow of the Royal Society. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of Subterraneal Treaſure. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>The Experienc'd Angler, the moſt ingenious on that Subject. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>The Serious Practice of Godlineſs. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>The Counteſs of <hi>Mortons</hi> Prayers. 24<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>Sure Footing in Chriſtianity examin'd, by <hi>G. H.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49191:16"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
